Register of the Anton Antonovich Dobkevich Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Anton Antonovich Dobkevich papers
1898-1923
2000C64
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Correspondence, military documents, and photographs, relating to Russian military activities in World War I, the Russian Civil War, and the Chinese Eastern Railway.
Dobkevich, Anton Antonovich, 1892-
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
A. A. Dobkevich was born on 18 January 1894 (1892 according to other records) in the city of Dubno. Commissioned as an officer upon graduation from the Kiev Military School in 1913 (1912) in the 3rd Zaamurskii pogranichnyi pekhotnyi polk, he transferred to the 6th Zaamurskii pogranichnyi pekhotnyi polk upon its departure for the front in February 1915. On the Southwestern (Russian) front of the First World War, he commanded the machine-gun detachment of an armored train and was appointed commander of the armored car "Zaamurets" in June 1916. Following this, Dobkevich served with the 1st Zaamurskii Zheleznodorozhnyi polk until his demobilization in 1918.
In April 1918, he was appointed deputy commander of the engineering section of the Russian forces of the extraterritorial zone of the Chinese Eastern Railway, and thereafter served in various capacities, including commander of an armored train, along the Chinese Eastern Railway until 1920. He emigrated to the United States in 1922, and died in California in January 1973.
Chronology
1892 January 18 (O. S.) Born, Dubno, Volynskaia guberniia, Russia
1910 Graduated, Pervyi Moskovskii kadetskii korpus
1912 Graduated, Kievskoe voennoe uchilishche Sub-Lieutenant, 3-ii Zaamurskii pogranichnyi pekhotnyi polk
1915 Transferred, 6-oi Zaamurskii pogranichnyi pekhotnyi polk Wounded and awarded St. George cross Transferred to 74 -yi Sibirskii oboznyi batalion
1916 Lieutenant, 2-ia Zaamurskaia zheleznodorozhnaia brigada
1918 Discharged from Russian army Enlisted, Chinese Eastern Railway security forces
1919 May-August Chief of staff, 1-aia partizanskaia kavaleriiskaia brigada
1919 August-1920 January Senior adjutant, Otdel'naia Amurskaia kazach'ia brigada
1920 July-1921 May Agent, Chinese Eastern Railway internal security
1922 Arrived in the United States
Scope and Content Note
The papers of A. A. Dobkevich relate primarily to his service in the First World War and Russian Civil War (in Ataman B. V. Annenkov's unit, on an armored train, and in the security forces of the Chinese Eastern Railway). The collection also includes a few family photographs, and his father's (Lt. Colonel A. F. Dobkevich) military service record (1914).
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Chinese Eastern Railway.; Russia. Armiia.; China.; Russia.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Biographical File, 1898-1923 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Birth certificate, identity papers, military service records and family papers, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1915-1923 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Miscellany, 1910s (Box 1)
  Diagram of an armored train and First World War field maps
- Photographs, 1910s-1922 (Box 1)
  One print depicting A. A. Dobkevich and twelve prints depicting family members and World War I scenes
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1898-1923 (Box 1)
  - Birth certificate (Folder 1: 1)
  - Educational records (Folder 1: 2)
  - Family file
    - Dobkevich, Anton Frantsevich (Folder 1: 3)
    - Dobkevich, Viktoriia Viktorovna (Folder 1: 4)
  - Identity certificate (Folder 1: 5)
  - Military service records.
    Includes orders, passes, commendations and similar matter
    - General. (Folder 1: 6)
      Brief service records
    - 1907-1917 (Folder 1: 7)
    - ., 1915 April-May (Folder 1: 8)
      Field order books and notes
    - 1918-1922 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 10)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1915-1923
  - General, 1923 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Unidentified, n.d. (Folder 1: 12)
  - Dobkevich, Viktoriia Viktorovna, 1915-1919 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Ignat'ev, Iosif Georgievich, 1923 (Folder 1: 14)
- MISCELLANY, [1910s]
  - Diagram of an armored train (Folder 1: 15)
  - Field maps, Russian front, World War One (Folder 1: 16)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1910s-1922
  - 10 prints depicting A. A. Dobkevich and family members (Folder 1: 17)
  - 3 prints depicting scenes of World War One (Folder 1: 18)